Guide to the William Holland Thomas papers, 1814-1900s and undated RL.01290
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Holland Thomas papers
1814-1900s and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thomas, William Holland, 1805-1893
RL.01290
30 Linear Feet
White agent and representative for the Cherokee, merchant, lawyer, and trader, of Haywood Co., N.C. Collection includes correspondence, account books, day books, ledgers, and other papers, relating to Thomas's life in western North Carolina; the removal of the Cherokee and the status of those who remained; the development of intrastructure including turnpikes and railroads in North Carolina; Civil War fighting in east Tennessee; postwar administration of Indian affairs; and his private business operations as a white trader among the Cherokees. Includes records of Thomas's five stores in Haywood and Cherokee counties, and business correspondence and accounts of Thomas's son, also William Holland Thomas, a merchant and farmer of Jackson County, N.C.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The William Holland Thomas papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library between 1938 and 1952, with an addition acquired in 2018.
Biographical Note
William Holland Thomas (1805-1893) was a white agent for the Cherokee in Western North Carolina. He also worked as a merchant, lawyer, and trader, based in Haywood Co., N.C. He also served as a colonel in the Confederate Army during the Civil War and led Thomas's Legion, which enlisted both Cherokee and Southern white recruits.
Collection Overview
Collection contains letters and papers of William H. Thomas (1805-1893) concerning his life and businesses in western North Carolina; his role as a white agent representing the Indians in negotiations and communications with the U.S. government; the removal of the Eastern Band of Cherokee on the Trail of Tears; the legal and financial conditions of Cherokee who remained behind in North Carolina; the building of roads and railroads through Western North Carolina; fighting during the Civil War in East Tennessee, including Thomas's leadership of Thomas's Legion in the Confederate Army; postwar administration of Indian affairs; and private business of Thomas, including some documentation of his declining health and his institutionalization for mental instability. There are also account books, day books, and ledgers showing a record of goods bought and sold in Thomas's five stores in Haywood and Cherokee counties. Included also are business correspondence and miscellaneous accounts, 1875-1890, of his son, William Holland Thomas, Jr., merchant and farmer of Jackson County, North Carolina.
Cherokee Indians -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Cherokee Indians -- Government relations; General stores -- North Carolina -- Cherokee County; Farmers -- North Carolina -- Jackson County; Cherokee County (N.C.) -- History; Tennessee -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Indians of North America -- North Carolina; Jackson County (N.C.) -- History; General stores -- North Carolina -- Haywood County; Haywood County (N.C.) -- History; Roads -- North Carolina; Merchants -- North Carolina -- Haywood County; Railroads -- North Carolina; Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians -- History; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Trail of Tears, 1838-1839; Confederate States of America. Army -- Officers -- Correspondence; Confederate States of America. Army. Thomas Legion
- General papers, 1814-1900s
  Scope and Contents
  Thomas's assorted correspondence along with extensive notes, loose account pages, and other miscellaneous items are sorted chronologically by year into General Papers. There are also volumes with travel diaries for various business ventures and letterbooks with copies of his incoming and outgoing correspondence. This series documents his various businesses and investments, his Confederate service during the Civil War, his work as an Indian agent, and his family life and friendships. Additional material on his work with the Eastern Band of Cherokee can be found in the Cherokee Papers Series; additional contracts, reports, and petitions relating to railroads and turnpikes can be found in the Infrastructure Series.
  - General papers, 1814-1842; 23 folders (Box 1)
  - General papers, 1843-1851; 11 folders (Box 2)
  - General papers, 1852-1874; 23 folders (Box 3)
  - General papers, 1875-1900s; 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Memorandum, correspondence, legal papers, notes, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1800s (Box 8)
  - Depositions, legal notes, etc., 1827-1843; Volume (boards); 16x19 cm; 150 pages (Volume M:3894)
    Scope and Contents note
    Haywood County, N.C. Copies of legal depositions, bills of sale, court judgments, and other cases regarding accusations of fraud, real estate exchanges, receipts, evidence, and memorandum.
  - Diary and Account Book, 1839-1841; Volume (paper); 10x15 cm; 82 pages (Volume S:3857)
    Haywood County, N.C.. Includes an account of a trip to Louisiana in March 1839.
  - Diary and Account Book, 1840; Volume (paper);; 20 pages (Volume S:3895)
    Haywood County, N.C. Thomas describes a trip to Athens, Georgia.
  - Letterbook, 1835-1842; Volume (boards); 20x32 cm; 76 pages (Volume L:3918)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Includes Scott's Creek store payments and bills, as well as copies of outgoing correspondence by Thomas regarding store and other business matters.
  - Letterbook, 1858; Volume (boards); 15x19 cm; 24 pages (Volume M:3920)
    Haywood County, N.C. Copies and abstract of letters sent by Thomas.
  - Account Book ("Journal of the business of Anson Banks and Co."), 1853, 1878; Volume (calf); 9.5x15 cm; 98 pages (Volume S:3861)
    Junaluska, Jackson County, N.C. Book originally included journal and account of the Anson Bangs Co. (1853), but was later annotated and supplemented with accounts from William H. Thomas, Jr. in 1878. A note on the inside cover explains how Thomas came into possession of of the book. On page 53, Thomas notes that his father was released from the asylum after one year on May 10, 1878.
- Financial and business papers, 1826-1890s
  This series includes a portion of Thomas's documentation regarding his business ventures and financial obligations. His account books and ledgers include a wide range of customer accounts, inventories, and store management records for stores he owned and operated in Murphy, Qualla Town, and Scott's Creek, North Carolina. There is also substantial additional material, including settlements of individual accounts, filed in the General Papers series and in the Cherokee Papers series.
  The account books and ledgers are in varying condition. Account books specifically dealing with Thomas's Cherokee customers have been filed in the Cherokee Papers series; additional assorted records of Thomas's business transactions with Cherokee can be found in this series or in General Papers.
  There is also a significant amount of receipts, some sorted loosely by date and some entirely unsorted. Though the bulk of these files are actually receipts, there are also invoices, bills, and other paper scraps related to financial exchanges of goods, labor, and products, including agricultural goods. There is some documentation of enslaved people being bought and sold.
  - Account Book, 1834-1836, Volume (boards); 20x34 cm.; 122 pages (Volume F:3849)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Contains a list of 16 "Rules of Shoal Creek Store," one of them being "Sell to all customers alike. Let not the price vary on any Article in order to do so keep the price of the goods marked on Each Article." Also contains customer accounts; billing accounts for leather, salt, and other goods; spending accounts for purchases in Augusta and Philadelphia.
  - Accounts, 1835-1839; Volume (boards); 20x38 cm.; 117 pages (Volume F:3850)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Customer accounts and retail prices. Includes notes from purchases in Augusta and Philadelphia.
  - Accounts, Records of Indebtedness and Inventory of Goods, 1836-1853; Volume (boards); 20x32 cm; 150 pages (Volume L:3851)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Includes accounts, lists of cash paid out on debts, and bills of articles carried forward; contents include hard ware, jewelry, crockery, among others.
  - Account Book: Inventory, Order Book, Notes and Accounts Due, Misc. Accounts, 1836-1841; Volume (boards); 20x31 cm; 160 pages (Volume L:3853)
    Indiantown / Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Multipurpose volume with sections listing customer accounts owed and due (including Cherokee accounts); inventories of stock; cash at the Indian Town stores; orders and debts from Thomas's purchases in Charleston and Philadelphia.
  - Account Book, 1837; Volume (paper); 10x15.5 cm; 34 pages (Volume S:3854)
    Haywood County, N.C. Records of Thomas's personal accounts. Also includes to-do lists.
  - Accounts ("Bill Book"), 1837-1838; Volume (boards); 16x38 cm.; 85 pages (Volume F:3855)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Expenses accrued by Thomas in Murphy, Athens, Ga., and Philadelphia. Also contains customer accounts and inventories of goods.
  - Accounts ("List of goods sold"); Day Book, 1845-1851; Volume (disbound); 20x32 cm; 205 pages (Volume L:3858)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Daybook "Sail book" listing purchases chronologically (1845-1849); account book listing purchases chronologically, grouped by customer name (1849-1851).
  - Account Book, 1849-1850; Volume (boards); 20x32 cm; 263 pages (Volume L:3859)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Customer accounts, including alphabetical index.
  - Account Book, 1864; Volume (calf); 9.5x13 cm; 36 pages (Volume S:3860)
    Haywood County, N.C. Includes accounts and lists of soldiers mustered into Thomas' Legion.
  - Accounts ("White Customers"), 1879-1880; Volume (calf and boards); 21x43 cm.; 350 pages (Volume F:3862)
    Junaluska, Jackson County, N.C. Largely blank book, with many torn-out pages; contains assorted notes by Thomas, some recording expenses and financial accounts but others relating to his travels and activities.
  - Accounts of Indebtedness, 1839-1842; Volume (boards); 20x31 cm; 80 pages (Volume L:3863)
    Murphy, Cherokee County, N.C. Lists of amounts due and brought over, including columns with officers and Cherokee accounts.
  - Cash Book, 1837-1872; Volume (boards); 16x20 cm; 200 pages (Volume M:3864)
    Calhoun, Tenn. Multi-purpose book with cash accounts, customer accounts, employee work records, memorandum and notes, as well as doodles and scribbles.
  - Cash Book, 1838 March; Volume (boards); 16.5x38.5 cm.; 100 pages (Volume F:3865)
    Haywood County, N.C. Largely blank book. Contains accounts of cash taken in and cash paid (and to whom), as well as some individuals' accounts. References "squaws," lists names of individual customers, perhaps Cherokees.
  - Collection Book, 1834-1838; Volume (boards); 16x39 cm.; 200 pages (Volume F:3866)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Customer/loan expenses and notations regarding repayment. Large portions blank.
  - Collection and Receipt Book, 1875-1880; Volume (boards); 19x31 cm; 50 pages (Volume L:3867)
    Junaluska, Jackson County, N.C. Multipurpose book with many marks, torn pages, etc. Assorted writings by Thomas, including his name many times. Also contains lists of accounts collected by Ferrill in 1875.
  - Day Book, 1832-1833; Volume (disbound); apprx. 16x40 cm.; unknown (Volume F:3868)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Daybook, with entries grouped by customer. Includes notations about Indian customers.
  - Day Book, 1833-1834; Volume (paper); 16x40 cm.; 280 pages (Volume F:3869)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Chronological daybook, with customer expenses at Scott's Creek store.
  - Day Book, 1834-1835; Volume (boards); 19x40 cm.; 231 pages (Volume F:3870)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Chronological daybook, with customer expenses and credits at Scott's Creek store.
  - Day Book, 1836-1838; Volume (boards); 15x41 cm; 428 pages (Volume F:3871)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Daybook. Includes laid-in booklet of pages, same size but separately bound (approx. 50 pages, includes index), documenting the settlement of accounts following the 1836 Treaty between the U.S. government and individual Cherokee families, with Thomas serving as agent. Regularly bound portion of the daybook contains chronological entries of customer accounts, 1836-1838. The end of the book has fold-out pages that seem to have been bound in later.
  - Day Book, 1836-1845; Volume (calf and boards); 17x47cm; 240 pages (Volume F:3872)
    Murphy, Cherokee County, N.C. Chronological daybook kept by Thomas and J.W. King with customer entries of expenses/sales for Valley / Valey River (1836-1837); Fort Delaney (1837-1838); and Murphy (1841?, 1843-1845).
  - Day Book, 1837; Volume (boards); 16x41 cm.; 300 pages (Volume F:3873)
    Indiantown, [Quallatown], Haywood County, N.C. Chronological daybook with customer entries of expenses/sales for Indian Town.
  - Day Book ("Day book for 1838 by J. W. King"), 1837-1839; Volume (boards); 16x39 cm.; 635 pages (Volume F:3874)
    Murphy, Cherokee County, N.C. Daybook, with entries grouped irregularly by date or by customer. Includes Thomas's notations about Indian and Negro customers.
  - Day Book, 1839; Volume (boards); 20x31 cm; 240 pages (Volume L:3875)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Chronological list of sales at Quallatown store for July-Dec. 1839.
  - Day Book, 1839-1840; Volume (boards); 20x32 cm; 240 pages (Volume L:3876)
    Murphy, Cherokee County, N.C. Murphy store chronological accounts including customer number/purchases, 1839 Sept-1840 Feb.
  - Day Book, 1839-1840; Volume (boards); 19x40 cm.; 138 pages (Volume F:3877)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Chronological daybook with customer expenses/credits for Scott's Creek. Includes some of Thomas's notations about Negro customers.
  - Day Book for Year 1840 Qualla Town, Volume (boards); 20x31 cm; 240 pages (Volume L:3878)
    Quallatown, Haywood Co., N.C. Quallatown store chronological list of customers/sales at store for Jan.-Aug. 1840.
  - Day Book, 1840-1841; Volume (boards); 19x31 cm; 220 pages (Volume L:3879)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Quallatown store chronological list of sales at store.
  - Day Book, 1832-1843; Volume (disbound (in cardboard boards)); 16x38 cm.; 100 pages (Volume F:3880)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Chronological daybook with customer entries for Scott's Creek and Weedan, N.C.
  - Day Book, 1841-1842; Volume (calf and boards); 18x40 cm; 578 pages (Volume L:3881)
    Murphy, Cherokee County, N.C. Chronological daybook with customer entries (name and number) for Murphy, N.C. Includes note: "Thomas and King commenced their copartnership at Murphy on the 8th day of April 1841."
  - Day Book, 1845-1848; Volume (calf); 21x33 cm; 475 pages (Volume L:3882)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Quallatown store chronological list of customers/sales at store for 1845 Dec.-1848 Oct.
  - Day Book, 1848-1850; Volume (boards); 20x32 cm; 256 pages (Volume L:3883)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Quallatown store chronological list of customers/sales at store for 1848-1850.
  - Day Book, 1851; Volume (boards); 21x33 cm; 100 pages (Volume L:3884)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Quallatown store chronological list of customers/sales at store for 1851 Mar.-Aug. Starts with page 260; other portions of book appear to have fallen out. Spine/binding loose.
  - Day Book ("Day Book White"), 1851-1853; Volume (calf and boards); 21x33 cm; 640 pages (Volume L:3885)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Quallatown store chronological list of customers/sales at store for 1851 July-1853 May.
  - Day Book ("Book B"), 1852-1854; Volume (boards); 20x32 cm; 260 pages (Volume L:3886)
    Fort Montgomery, Cherokee County, N.C. Fort Montgomery store customer/sales chronologically listed 1852-1854.
  - Day Book ("Qualla Town Day book for 1854"), 1855; Volume (boards); 20x32 cm; 185 pages (Volume L:3888)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Quallatown store chronological list of customers/sales at store for 1855 Feb.-June.
  - Day Book ("Qualla Town Day Book Farmer's Journal"), 1854 June 27-1855 June 2; Volume (boards); 22x34 cm; 235 pages (Volume F:3889)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Chronological daybook with customer entries (name and purchase) for Qualla Town.
  - Day Book, 1854-1857; Volume (boards); 20x32 cm; 150 pages (Volume L:3890)
    Fort Montgomery, Cherokee County, N.C. Fort Montgomery store customer/sales chronologically listed 1854-1857. Back half of the book is blank.
  - Day Book ("Wm. H. Thomas Day Book for Qualla Town NC"), 1855-1856; Volume (boards); 21x34 cm; 292 pages (Volume F:3891)
  - Day Book ("Wm. H. Thomas's Day Book"), 1856-1857; Volume (boards); 20x37 cm; 475 pages (Volume F:3892)
  - Day Book, 1858 Apr. 29-1863 Mar. 4; Volume (calf); 17x41 cm; 530 pages (Volume F:3893)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Chronological daybook with customer entries (name and purchase) for Qualla Town. Includes stitched in mini-quire in the front with title "Private accts at Qualla Town store for which R. Watts is responsible," dated 1859-1862.
  - Index to Ledger for 1847, Volume (paper); 12x33 cm; approx 50 (Volume ff:3896)
    Haywood County, N.C. Alphabetical index with customer names and assigned number.
  - Invoice Book and Day Book, 1838-1840; Volume (boards); 16.5x40.5 cm; 80 pages (Volume F:3899)
    Murphy, Cherokee County, N.C. Multi-purpose volume. Pages 1-8 appear to be invoice lists. On page 9 the book's entries become more like a daybook, with customer expenses from 1840 listed chronologically. Also includes a copied contract on the back page.
  - Journal and Day Book, 1836-1838; Volume (calf); unknown; 424 pages (Volume F:3900)
    Indiantown, [Quallatown], Haywood County, N.C. Volume with two distinct sections: pages 1-238 are customer accounts; the latter half of the book (about 180 pages) is a daybook recording purchases at Indian Town between January and July 1838. Also includes Rules of the Store at the end.
  - Journal and Day Book, 1840-1844; Volume (calf); 26x38 cm; 633 pages (Volume F:3901)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Volume with two distinct sections: pages 1-156 are customer accounts; the latter half of the book (about 180 pages) is a daybook recording purchases at Quallatown in 1842.
  - Land Book for Cherokee County, 1838-1853; Volume (calf and boards); 20x32 cm; 86 pages (Volume F:3903)
    Murphy, Cherokee County, N.C. Multi-purpose volume with land sales and customer accounts.
  - Ledger, 1833-1834; Volume (paper); 21x33 cm; 134 pages (Volume ff:3904)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Customer accounts with Scott's Creek store.
  - Ledger, 1835-1837; Volume (calf); 20x33 cm; 142 pages (Volume F:3905)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Customer accounts. Includes index at the front.
  - Ledger, 1836-1838; Volume (calf and boards); 26x37 cm; 419 pages (Volume F:3906)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Customer accounts detailing purchases, including a name index at the front.
  - Ledger, 1836-1845; Volume (calf and boards); 18x43 cm; 310 pages (Volume F:3907)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Customer accounts.
  - Ledger, 1837-1867; Volume (calf and boards); 23x33 cm; 425 pages (Volume F:3908)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Customer account book, including indices. Cherokee customers are included.
  - Ledger, 1839-1844; Volume (calf and boards); 21x32 cm; 497 pages (Volume L:3909)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Customer accounts ledger, with alphabetical index for customer names. Pages 266-462 are blank. Later entries are miscellaneous notes, including some references to Indian chiefs' payments and other store expenses/credits.
  - Ledger, 1839-1845; Volume (calf and boards); 27x38 cm; 550 pages (Volume F:3910)
    Cherokee County, N.C. Customer accounts, including an index. Book only partially used; pages 337-342 are "disbursement of the old concern". Pages 345-544 are blank. Page 545-546 have "expenses paid out of the new firm for building".
  - Ledger and Day Book, 1839-1841; Volume (calf and boards); 26x38 cm; 630 pages (Volume F:3911)
    Murphy, Cherokee County, N.C. Daybook. First portion of the book has customer accounts, by name; volume then shifts to recording purchases and expenses chronologically.
  - Ledger, 1840-1845; Volume (calf and boards); 25x38 cm; 620 pages (Volume F:3913)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Customer accounts, including periodic indices with alphabetical lists. Includes inlaid clipping.
  - Ledger (Postage Accounts), 1844-1845; Volume (boards); 16x18 cm; 200 pages (Volume M:3915)
    Murphy, Cherokee County, N.C. Includes index and accounts with individuals noting postage paid on various goods, mail, and newspaper subscriptions.
  - Ledger, 1845-1848; Volume (calf and boards); 22x34 cm; 430 pages (Volume F:3916)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Customer accounts of purchases; indexed by name each year.
  - Ledger ("Wm H. Thomas's White Book"), 1847-1855; Volume (calf and boards); 21x33 cm; 620 pages (Volume F:3917)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C. Customer accounts; index in the front, rest of the volume has customer names with chronological entries of purchases.
  - Letterbook and Accounts ("Receipt book Old Firm"), 1837-1845; Volume (boards); 20x32 cm; 350 pages (Volume L:3919)
    Murphy, Cherokee County, N.C. Accounts/payments received; records of work (including construction, brick paving); copies of outgoing correspondence for business at the Murphy Store. Pages 33-175 blank. Later pages have assorted blank segments. Some letters composed upside down.
  - List of White Accounts, Notes, Judgements, Etc., 1849-1867; Volume (boards); 15.5x25.5 cm; 46 pages (Volume M:3921)
    Haywood County, N.C. Customer accounts.
  - Miscellaneous Accounts, 1874; Volume (calf); 8x12 cm; 80 pages (Volume S:3922)
    Haywood County, N.C. Entries mostly illegible.
  - Financial papers, notes, bills, accounts, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Disbound account books, miscellaneous, 1840s-1860s; 2 folders (Box 4)
    Includes George Gibbons book fragments.
  - Receipts, 1834-1900s; 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Unsorted receipts, approximately 1830s-1870s; 15 folders (Box 7, Box 8)
- Infrastructure papers, 1828-1859; undated
  Assorted materials relating to Thomas's work on various railroad and turnpike boards and as a community leader advocating for infrastructure expansion to Western North Carolina. Items include General Assembly acts, copies of company minutes and contracts, petitions by various communities and citizens asking the state for turnpikes and railroad stops, and surveys and statistics regarding the building and planning for transportation needs throughout the region.
  - Report of engineers upon a canal connecting the Okoa and Connesauga rivers, in Tennessee and Alabama, 1828 (Box 4)
  - Draft excerpts, incomplete, of notes and other writings re: railroad, approximately 1851 (Box 4)
  - Railroad company articles of incorporation (incomplete), 1851 Jan. 28 (Box 4)
  - A condensed statement of statistics taken from the Report of the Board of Public Works of Virginia, 1851 (Box 4)
  - Railroad statistics from the Board of Internal Improvement of Virginia, 1852 (Box 5)
  - Petition for the extension of the N.C. railroad west, signed by 600 citizens W. of Buncombe County, 1852 (Box 5)
  - Rail Road meeting, Rabun Co., N.C., 1852 Feb. 23 (Box 5)
  - Petition of Jackson Co. citizens to N.C. General Assembly requesting a charter for a turnpike road, 1854 Sept. 26 (Box 5)
  - Railroad Statistics, 1854-1855; Volume (paper); 9x14.5 cm; 30 pages (Volume S:3923)